Guide to the Philo T. and Elma G. Farnsworth audio collection. 1960-1978
Multimedia Archives, J. Willard Marriott Library, University of Utah
- 1975, Compact disc (Disc 18)
  - "Agnes and Ethyl Rush" 9/1/75 Side 1., 1975 (Track 17)
    Agnes tells a story of Phil going to get a bucket of milk at age eight in heavy snow. He took a long time to bring it back and her mother kept looking out the door. Eventually, she saw just a bucket above the snow, as it was so deep as to almost cover him.
    They all talk about Phil's ability to accomplish vast amounts of work and achieve great things.
  - "Agnes and Ethyl Rush" 9/1/75 Side 2., 1975 (Track 17)
    Pem says she has briefs of the case where Phil won the decision against RCA in the invention of the electric television. She says they spent about thirty thousand dollars defending themselves and were thankful that RCA chose not to appeal the ruling in a civil court because she and Phil didn't have much more money and would have struggled to continue to fight.
    They talk about missing books of day to day office operations that they wish they could find.
    Pem talks about all the different institutions looking for materials that Phil wrote or that mention him.
    She is concerned that if she isn't able to find them first she will be unable to access them.
- 1975, Compact disc (Disc 19)
  - "Agnes and Ethyl Rush" 9/1/75 Side 2 Part 2., 1975 (Track 17)
    Pem says that they were unable to stand being in Maine after the house burned down, but they eventually went back and built a cabin on the pond that their house had overlooked in 1966. At one time they owned over 3000 acres of land in Maine.
    They tell stories about a man named Herb Metcalf.
    They talk about Ruth and how impressed they are with her despite her struggles with age or possibly a singular incident, it's difficult to tell exactly.
    About five minutes of blank tape at the end of the track.
  - "Cliff" 9/28/75 Side 1., 1975 (Track 18)
    Cliff says that he remembers Mary Pickford as being the first image on television, Pem says it was Mickey Mouse because of the higher contrast. He says the first time he remembers really believing television would be big was when he found himself subconsciously focused on the content instead of the quality of the image during 1928.
    Cliff and Pem both tell a story of a Christmas party getting out of control and they laugh about it.
    Pem tells a story of taking a cab from a driver who was rude and took a longer route to get more money so they ended up tipping him a nickel and then taking it back after he made a disgusted face.
    Cliff remarks that he was always impressed most with Phil's ability to multi-task and handle such a huge variety and volume of tasks.
    She notes that there is a large gap in Phil's journal from September to October of the year that there was a fire in the lab and asks why that might have been because he was usually so meticulous about writing regularly.
    He tells a story about missing rent payments for three months and not being kicked out and says he was amazed by the generosity and trust that he was shown which he didn't expect in a bigger city
- 1975, Compact disc (Disc 20)
  - "Cliff" 9/28/75 Side 2., 1975 (Track 18)
    He tells a story of losing control of a truck going down a canyon but being able to stop it by riding it up against a clay wall.
    He talks about picking cherries and taking them on a ten hour drive to sell them where he would get forty or fifty dollars for them which he thought was a good price.
    He tells a story of going to the opening night of the Fox Theater in San Francisco and listening to Will Rogers speak.
    Pem tells a story about when they all drove down from Maine to North Carolina in their new Cadillac.
    Phil put a dent in it and they all found the following exchange with the police officer to be very funny.
    There are approximately four minutes of empty space at the end of the disc.
- 1975, Compact disc (Disc 21)
  - "Cliff, Phil, and Pem" 9/28/75 Side 1., 1975 (Track 19)
    He describes the method for creating a crystal control units for radio stations, which they spent a few months creating after their lab was shut down and funding was stopped for a period of time.
    They talk about the fire that destroyed a ton of equipment in their lab. The firefighters were scared to go in because some of the chemicals had exploded due to contact with either the fire or water.
    He talks about the process for creating tubes, saying that six inches was about the largest that they did at that time. They talk about how they had considered a ten inch tube but didn't end up completing it.
    He talks about experiences with tubes exploding while he was holding them as well as mercury thermometers cracking in the oven.
    The same story from before about another employee taking his safety light and eventually being fired for it comes up again.
    There are approximately fifteen minutes of empty space at the end of the disc.
- 1975, Compact disc (Disc 22)
  - "Cliff, Phil, and Pem" 9/28/75 Side 2., 1975 (Track 19)
    She found a drawing of a flat bottom tube from 1927, but he claims that it was just a drawing and there is no way he had completed one at that time.
    He says early on they made their own ovens for the tubes.
    At the time they couldn't buy Cesium, so they would create it instead. He describes their process for doing this.
    He tells a story of getting potassium in his eyes and washing them out quickly to avoid damage.
    They spend some time reading Phil's journal to ascertain when they were experimenting with different ideas.
    There are approximately seven minutes of empty space at the end of the disc.
- 1976, Compact disc (Disc 23)
  - Excerpts from Author Crawford tape Side 1., No date given. (Track 20)
    Pem interviews a cousin of Philo's father.
    Pem tells a story of Phil working as an electrician at the railroad one winter despite not being 21, which apparently was required.
    Crawford says that when he was attending the University of Utah and taking physics classes he would often have Phil study with him because he was so good at it.
    This is a tape where Pem is playing the tape and occasionally talking over it or giving notes while it is playing.
  - "Art" 1/30/76 Side 1, Part 1., 1976 (Track 21)
    Pem is talking to a man named Don, who began to work with Phil in February of 1936 in Philadelphia.
    He says he was originally interested in the music of television but became more interested in radio electronics over time.
    He talks about working with John Stagnaro on a couple of projects, included a guided missile, although it was not frequently used.
    He first received a music degree from Temple University before going back to school at Purdue and receiving a degree in electrical engineering.
    In 1949 he was sent to Princeton by RCA to work on the development of the color television.
    He talks about various issues with color TVs from different companies at the time and its change over time.
- 1976, Compact disc (Disc 24)
  - "Art" 1/30/76 Side 1, Part 2., 1976 (Track 21)
    He notes that the biggest reason that color TV had improved dramatically was due to the improvement of the lenses, not of the tubes in the television itself.
    He describes the filming of a space launch. They had to record it in case something went wrong because they did not want to broadcast a failed launch. At that time video tape recorders were just becoming available. He says he was able to work something out with a friend of his who was working with these tape recorders at the time.
  - "Art" 1/30/76 Side 2, Part 1., 1976 (Track 21)
    He tells a story of being in China and being told to move their camera after a telephone pole partially obstructed a giant portrait of Chairman Mao.
    He also recounts his experiences working with the Japanese government and different Japanese companies.
    She says that Phil was very excited to work with him because of his broad range of interests.
    They talk about some of the trends in the music business specifically the use of synthesizers in music.
    They talk about Phil's ability to inspire others to work harder with his own great work ethic and attitude about work.
    The last six minutes they listen to a couple of arrangements that he had made on records. He says that he worked on this at the same time that he was working in the lab.
  - "Art" 1/30/76 Side 2, Part 2., 1976 (Track 21)
    The name of the track is the same but I don't believe that the man on the other tapes is the same as the man on this one. He sounds different.
    He describes a situation where they were trying to have a new metal piece built and they visited many metallurgists who after charging a consulting fee were all unable to do it. They finally asked a local company that had done some work for them and they were able to make it work, which he found very amusing.
    He moved to Las Vegas in 1931 and stayed there ever since.
- 1976, Compact disc (Disc 25)
  - "Ruth L." 5/6/76 Side 1., 1976 (Track 22)
    Four or five people including Pem and her Son go to visit Ruth who seems to be in the hospital. They talk about how the stocks she has can cover her medical expenses as well as a couple of other options.
    They seem to record it for her to listen to later.
    It's not totally clear if she's listening at the time or is sleeping.
  - "ITT" 4/23/76 Side 1., 1976 (Track 23)
    She talks to someone about the things that came out of Phil's work. He talks about something as a pattern or fault recognition device.
    The iotron tube had been used in airports at some point but he doesn't know if it's still in use in this capacity.
    The two men she's talking to say that ITT did not store any records other than those which are required by the IRS and are unlikely to have anything of historical value in terms of paperwork from when Phil worked at ITT.
  - "ITT" 4/23/76 Side 2., 1976 (Track 23)
    Pem talks about her experience interviewing Cliff, and how helpful he has been even though he was unsure he would remember very much.
    They talk about who at ITT might be able to provide her with more information about what she's looking for. She doesn't think she'll be able to interview him because he's leaving on vacation that evening and she won't be able to come back.
    They discuss a couple of other people she could try to interview but they're unsure where these people actually are at the moment.
- 1976, Compact disc (Disc 26)
  - "Skee Turner" Side 1, No date given. (Track 24)
    Pem talks about many people being let go when they moved from Philco. They struggle to remember how many people were kept and how many were let go.
    Skee said he had a huge amount of records and photos but they burned in a fire.
    Skee talks about a business agreement they had with the Baird Company and their work on another deal with a German company named Fernseh.
    They talk about his negotiation on the royalty clause of the contract with the German company, and they were unable to find a deal that satisfied both parties.
    They walked away from the deal initially but came back to the same company and were able to find a deal that satisfied both parties.
    He talks about their anxiety to start actually moving forward with productions of television as opposed to simply research.
    They talk about the start of world war two and how they had hoped that the development of the television would help to curb war in general.
    There are approximately three minutes of empty space at the end of the tape.
  - "Interview with KSL man for inventors' conference" 5/76., 1976 (Track 24)
    RCA challenged whether Phil was the inventor of the dissector tube which powered the television. The final hearing was in 1934. She tells the story of another man jumping out the window after being sued by RCA and losing all of his money.
    There is a very loud airplane that makes it difficult to hear what is said for a minute or so.
    Before the interview itself, you get to hear them discuss what they will talk about in the interview.
    Dr. Zworykin challenged that he had developed the tube before Phil, but through cross questioning they found out that he was unaware how his tube actually worked. RCA believed that Phil could not have possibly developed his tube as a thirteen to fifteen year old.
    Pem says that Phil would sympathize with inventors in the United States because it is so difficult to fight a large corporation because the inventor must give so much control to the company that helps to finance them.
    She discusses his other inventions as well as his television related patents.
    She tries to describe his habits and thought processes and the way that he worked on inventions.
    She talks about his disinterest in writing papers or articles and how it contributed to his lack of credit for many of his inventions.
    They look through a photo album that Pem has and they decide on pictures that will be used.
    She says that working in a small group helped Phil's ability to complete his television project because they didn't have many of the same guidelines and rules that restricted what the engineers at larger companies were able to do.
    She once again begins to talk about photos that she is showing the interviewer.
    The last few minutes of the tape are blank, it is unclear if they forgot it was running or what happened.
- 1976, Compact disc (Disc 27)
  - "Herman Phleger at Sutter St. office, S.F." 5/7/76 Side 1., 1976 (Track 25)
    They went to Philadelphia to set up Philco's laboratory because they were the first company to license many of Phil's patents.
    They left after a couple of years to go to Fort Wayne, Indiana to form Farnsworth television to manufacture their own televisions.
    They talk about one of the men who sold his stock just before it dropped significantly and was accused of insider trading, although it was found to just be coincidence in the end.
    They talk about some investors who ended up not really making any money but helping to finance some of Phil's work.
    They talk about a time where all the holders of stock in the company put forth a proportionate amount of money to build the laboratory.
    They talk about corporations in California and how they used to not be limited liability until they realized that this was really hindering their ability to attract corporations because of stockholder liability.
    He says that Phil was very fortunate to come into contact with responsible decent investors who didn't take advantage of him.
    The last few minutes of the disc are blank.
  - "EXEL – 90 Mins. – Frances Critchlaro, Philo, and Pem" 5/25/76 Side 1, Part 1., 1976 (Track 26)
    Frances says Phil was in 6th grade when he came to Rigby, Idaho. She says that this was just after the end of World War 1 and there was an influenza epidemic around the same time.
    Frances taught Phil music in 7th, 8th, and 9th grade, but only taught him for home room in 6th grade.
    Pem tells a story about Phil making cream puffs and having a bottle of turpentine in the cupboard above that must have been poured in.
- 1976, Compact disc (Disc 28)
  - "EXEL – 90 Mins. – Frances Critchlaro, Philo, and Pem" 5/25/76 Side 1, Part 2., 1976 (Track 26)
    Very short part, only five minutes.
    They talk about who was principle at the time and why she left the school, which she says was because they cut the music program.
  - "At Jim Heiniyo – Fusor Group" 7/76, 1976 (Track 27)
    They talk to Cy Day who is difficult to understand.
    There are multiple people talking in the background and the conversation is often less focused than in many of the other interviews.
    Because of the people speaking in the background and jumping in and out of the conversation, it's often difficult to hear what is said.
    After about twenty minutes, the setting changes and there are no longer other people talking in the background.
    They get into some of the specifics of Phil's beliefs relating to what was most efficient in terms of energy.
    They talk a little bit about some of the things they built and the designs.
    There are approximately forty minutes of blank space at the end of the track.
- 1976, Compact disc (Disc 29)
  - "EXEL – 90 Mins. – Frances Critchlaro, Philo, and Pem" 5/25/76, 1976 (Track 26)
    Blank CD no audio.
- 1976, Compact disc (Disc 30)
  - "At Jim Heiniyo – Fusor Group" 7/76 Side 2., 1976 (Track 27)
    They talk about a man named Charlie who sold his business for two or three million dollars and how frugal he and his wife were when they were first married.
    They seem to be at a party of sorts or something and people keep coming up and talking to them. Much like the first side of this tape, it makes it a little bit harder to follow.
    Pem says that someone has decided to make a made-for-television movie about Phil's life.
    One of them talks about the development of the Fusor and how many of the things that are taken for granted now were things that they figured out during that time.
  - "Fritz Furth at Belines" 8/24/76 Side 1., 1976 (Track 28)
    Fritz talks about his experiences with Phil. He recalls that Phil was called into his office to help design a specific tube that they needed. The tube was designed to help in the navigation of airplanes.
    They talk a little bit about the iotron tube and its various applications and the struggles they had in creating and building it. EGG was the main purchaser of the iotron tube during this time.
    He talks about a couple of presentations that they put together and talks about how some people thought it had real potential and others were highly skeptical.
    Pem talks about the difficulty of crediting Philo with all that he did while not stretching the truth and maintaining credibility.
    They talk about what they believe contributed the most to Phil's victory over RCA in regards to the invention of the image dissector tube. They had both thought that it was primarily because of Justin Tollman's ability to recall what Phil had told him, but were surprised that another source had claimed that it was mostly because of Professor Zworykin's inability to produce a working dissector tube of his own.
- 1976, Compact disc (Disc 31)
  - "Fritz Furth at Belines" 8/24/76 Side 2., 1976 (Track 28)
    He says that he has a picture of Phil with the Fusor which Pem is excited about since she believes she had lost her only picture of him with the Fusor.
    They talk about Phil's math frequently confusing them and the difficulties that this caused at times.
    This is a short track, only about seven minutes.
  - "At Tobe Rutherford's – Tobe, Philo III, Rem" 8/25/76 Side 1., 1976 (Track 29)
    They talk about Phil flying east to make a presentation to Bell Labs and the difficulty that cross-country flights had at the time. Pem says there was a storm that forced them to land and take part of the trip by train. It's not entirely clear whether they are saying that this is what happened, but they talk about passengers being brought along on mail planes for a period of time.
    They talk about Bell Labs, who were interested in Phil's work and had increased cesium sensitivity dramatically in one of their products. This was important because cesium was difficult to obtain.
    Tobe tells a story about Phil leaving for a week and while he was gone everyone in the lab was fired.
    Tobe says he was laid off for about a month after this and that it was the longest he was ever laid off.
    Tobe tells a story about Phil's fixing a major problem and how surprised they were that he was able to solve it rather simply.
    Tobe talks about Phil's belief that everyone he hired was working with him, not for him. He also says that they were not worried about layoffs partly because of Phil's attitude and ability to lead them.
  - "At Tobe Rutherford's – Tobe, Philo III, Rem" 8/25/76 Side 2 Part 1., 1976 (Track 29)
    Tobe tells a story about a man named Baird (?) who toured their facility and saw their setup but didn't believe it would work. They laugh about his reaction when Phil demonstrated it for him because he had made a somewhat snarky remark just before.
    They talk about Phil not getting the credit he deserved primarily because he was not particularly concerned with getting any of his ideas published in academic journals.
    Tobe talks about Phil's invention of the television tube and says that he took a fundamentally different approach than most did.
- 1976, Compact disc (Disc 32)
  - "At Tobe Rutherford's – Tobe, Philo III, Rem" 8/25/76 Side 2 Part 2., 1976 (Track 29)
    They talk about Ski and although they all say he wasn't usually an integral part of the business, they recount a story where he was able to shift an early negotiation in England dramatically in their favor.
    They talk about the end of Phil's time at Philco and how unhappy the company was when he left.
    Tobe tells a story about Philco trying to license RCA patents for less than they should by selling items from one company to another rather than directly to consumers because the price for licensing was based on income. This didn't work.
    At that time, Philco was licensing radio patents from RCA and television patents from Farnsworth, giving them advanced royalties on projected sales under the condition that the Farnsworth lab would move to Philco.
    After the television research had sufficiently developed, they brought in their own engineers and tried to ensure that eventually they would no longer need to give these advances to Farnsworth.
    Tobe believed that the company board at Philco was extremely interested in getting in early on the television, not necessarily one main person unlike at RCA where Sarnov was clearly the most interested.
  - "At Tobe Rutherford's – Tobe, Philo III, Rem" 8/25/76 Side 1., 1976 (Track 30)
    They spend time talking about the current state of people that worked on the television project with them.
    There are twenty six minutes of blank space at the end of the tape.
- 1976, Compact disc (Disc 33)
  - "Alice Yarish, Examiner Interview" 8/26/76 Side 1., 1976 (Track 31)
    Sound quality is very poor, lots of background noise.
    Alice is interviewing Philo III and Pem, asking them what they plan to do for the fiftieth anniversary of the invention of television. They plan to use original parts to demonstrate what Phil had created.
    The tape is of them being interviewed, not the interview itself. They often talk to Alice, she tells people to take pictures, and there is other cross talk as well.
    This demonstration is scheduled for September 7th, 1976. They first projected a straight line because it was easily distinguishable from the horizontal noise of the early projections.
    They seem to show her some of the materials but are very cautious about showing it to her because it is so fragile.
    The photographer takes a number of pictures, which is apparent because of the sound of the camera shutter in the background.
    The tube that they have at the moment is made by Cliff, as were the original tubes.
    Philo describes Cliff's background to Alice, helping to explain where he came from and how he became what he is now.
    They plan to host media and people who worked in the Farnsworth shop originally at the demonstration on September 7th, but from the 8th going forward he says that there will be an ongoing exhibit in the museum.
    They talk about a man named Paul Schatzkin who is interested in working with them on a made for TV movie about Phil and the invention of the television.
    They describe to Alice the RCA lawsuit against Farnsworth and how it worked and why Farnsworth was able to win despite much less money.